<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Authors | Skanda Vaidyanath</title>
    <link>https://skandavaidyanath.github.io/authors/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://skandavaidyanath.github.io/authors/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Authors</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language>
    <image>
      <url>https://skandavaidyanath.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Authors</title>
      <link>https://skandavaidyanath.github.io/authors/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://skandavaidyanath.github.io/authors/admin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://skandavaidyanath.github.io/authors/admin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am a final year undergraduate student of computer science at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bits-pilani.ac.in/hyderabad/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;BITS Pilani, Hyderabad Campus&lt;/a&gt;. My research interests include reinforcement learning, deep learning and natural language processing. I like thinking about and working on different applications of RL in the real world - like dialogue systems and human swarm interactions, etc. I&amp;rsquo;m also interested in thinking about the modeling of RL problems and I often find myself asking the question &amp;lsquo;What are the properties of a good state space/reward function?&amp;rsquo;. Recently, I&amp;rsquo;ve also found the idea of meta learning very fascinating and has made me think of the question &amp;lsquo;Can I teach an agent that has learned to play tennis, to play badminton?&amp;rsquo;. I find neural networks very fascinating and often think about how backpropagation works in different deep learning models. A lot of my work also involves NLP and I am very interested in exploring the intersection of NLP and RL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am currently pursuing my undergraduate thesis at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mpi-inf.mpg.de/departments/databases-and-information-systems/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Max Planck Institute for Informatics&lt;/a&gt; under &lt;a href=&#34;https://andrewyates.net/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dr. Andrew Yates&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://paramitamirza.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dr. Paramita Mirza&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past I&amp;rsquo;ve had the good fortune of working closely with some amazing researchers such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bits-pilani.ac.in/hyderabad/bhanumurthy/Profile&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Prof. N. L. Bhanu Murthy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://universe.bits-pilani.ac.in/hyderabad/arunamalapati/Profile&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Prof. Aruna Malapati&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://people.ict.usc.edu/~kgeorgila/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Prof. Kallirroi Georgila&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://ict.usc.edu/profile/david-traum/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Prof. David Traum&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in my work or would like to chat about technical interests we might share, feel free to get in touch!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
